Sabbir Ahmed

Email: sabbirahmed@iut-dhaka.edu | Phone: (880) 1754221481 | Website: ggck43.github.io Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=I_Dk4ZoAAAAJ

About

I am working as an Assistant Professor in the Department of CSE at the Islamic University of Technology (IUT). At present, I am a member of the Computer Vision lab, advised by Prof. Hasanul Kabir. Before that, I received my M.Sc. and B.Sc. (Gold medalist) in CSE from IUT, respectively, in the years 2022 and 2017. My current research is in improving few-shot learning algorithms for image classification tasks. Besides, I've worked with different applications of deep learning in the fields of Computer Vision and Natural Language Processing, such as leaf disease classification, gait analysis, traffic sign detection, text summarization, handwritten digit recognition, etc.

Education

• M.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering

Department of CSE, Islamic University of Technology

Thesis: Classification of Plant Disease from Leaf images using Few-shot Learning

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Hasanul Kabir, Professor, IUT

• B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering (First Class First - IUT Gold Medalist)

2014 - 2017

Department of CSE, Islamic University of Technology

Higher Secondary School Certificate (HSC)
 Chittagong College

2011 - 2012

Experience

Assistant Professor

September 2022 - Present

Department of CSE, Islamic University of Technology

Courses conducted: Pattern Recognition, Data Structures, Algorithms, Big Data Analysis, Linear Algebra Official responsibilities: Routine preparation, Exam coordination, Question moderation, Course load distribution, Student advisor for third year.

Club responsibilities: Advisor - IUT Computer Society (IUTCS), IUT Programming Community (IUTPC)

• Lecturer 2018 - August 2022
Department of CSE, Islamic University of Technology

Publications

Journals (5)

- 1. Tasnim Ahmed, Shahriar Ivan, Ahnaf Munir, and **Sabbir Ahmed**. "Decoding depression: Analyzing social network insights for depression severity assessment with transformers and explainable AI." Natural Language Processing Journal (2024), Elsevier.
- 2. Md Bakhtiar Hasan, Tasnim Ahmed, **Sabbir Ahmed**, and Md Hasanul Kabir. "GaitGCN++: Improving GCN-based gait recognition with part-wise attention and DropGraph." Journal of King Saud University-Computer and Information Sciences, Elsevier (2023)
- 3. ABM Ashikur Rahman, Md Bakhtiar Hasan, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Tasnim Ahmed, Md Hamjajul Ashmafee, Mohammad Ridwan Kabir, and Md Hasanul Kabir. "Two decades of Bengali handwritten digit recognition: A survey." *IEEE Access* 10 (2022)
- 4. **Sabbir Ahmed**, Md Bakhtiar Hasan, Tasnim Ahmed, Md Redwan Karim Sony, and Md Hasanul Kabir. "Less is more: lighter and faster deep neural architecture for tomato leaf disease classification." *IEEE Access* 10 (2022)
- 5. Mohammed A. Alanezi, Mohammad S. Shahriar, Md Bakhtiar Hasan, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Yusuf A. Sha'aban, and Houssem REH Bouchekara. "Livestock management with unmanned aerial vehicles: A review." *IEEE Access* (2022)

Conferences (20)

- 1. Shahriar Ivan, Tasnim Ahmed, **Sabbir Ahmed**, and Md Hasanul Kabir. "A Vision-Language Multimodal Framework for Detecting Hate Speech in Memes." In CCECE (2024), IEEE, Canada.
- 2. Tasnim Ahmed, Md Bakhtiar Hasan, **Sabbir Ahmed**, and Md Hasanul Kabir. "ExE-Net: Explainable Ensemble Network for Potato Leaf Disease Classification." In CCECE (2024), IEEE, Canada.
- 3. Syem Aziz, Nokimul Hasan Arif, Sakif Ahbab, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Tasnim Ahmed, and Md Hasanul Kabir. "Improved Speech Emotion Recognition in Bengali Language using Deep Learning." In 26th ICCIT (2023), IEEE, Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh.
- 4. Mohtasim Hadi Rafi, Mohammad Ratul Mahjabin, Md Sabbir Rahman, Md Hasanul Kabir, and **Sabbir Ahmed**. "A Critical Analysis of Deep Learning Applications in Crop Pest Classification: Promising Pathways and Limitations." In 26th ICCIT (2023), IEEE, Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh.
- Sidratul Tanzila Tasmi, Sabbir Ahmed, and Md Mohsin Sarker Raihan. "Performance Analysis of Machine Learning Algorithms for Autism Spectrum Disorder Level Detection using Behavioural Symptoms." In 26th ICCIT (2023), IEEE, Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh.
- 6. Tauseef Tajwar, Muftiqur Rahman, Taukir Azam Chowdhury, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Moshiur Farazi, and Md Hasanul Kabir. "Improving Zero-Shot Semantic Segmentation using Dynamic Kernels." In *DICTA (2023)*, IEEE, Australia.
- Alvi Khan, Fida Kamal, Nuzhat Nower, Tasnim Ahmed, Sabbir Ahmed, and Tareque Chowdhury. "NERvous About My Health: Constructing a Bengali Medical Named Entity Recognition Dataset", EMNLP Findings (2023), ACL, Singapore
- 8. Ridwan Mahbub, Ifrad Khan, Samiha Anuva, Md Shihab Shahriar, Md Tahmid Rahman Laskar, and **Sabbir Ahmed**. "Unveiling the Essence of Poetry: Introducing a Comprehensive Dataset and Benchmark for Poem Summarization", *EMNLP Main (2023)*, ACL, Singapore.
- 9. Alvi Khan, Fida Kamal, Mohammad Abrar Chowdhury, Tasnim Ahmed, Md Tahmid Rahman Laskar, and Sabbir Ahmed. "BanglaCHQ-Summ: An Abstractive Summarization Dataset for Medical Queries in Bangla Conversational Speech", *EMNLP BLP workshop (2023)*, ACL, Singapore.
- 10. Asaduzzaman Herok, and Sabbir Ahmed. "Cotton Leaf Disease Identification Using Transfer Learning", 2nd ICICT4SD (2023), IEEE, Dhaka, Bangladesh.
- 11. Rafid Haque, ABM Ashikur Rahman, and **Sabbir Ahmed**. "Data-Driven Analysis and Forecasting of COVID-19 Third Wave in SAARC Countries", 2nd ICICT4SD (2023), IEEE, Dhaka, Bangladesh.
- 12. Tasnim Ahmed, Ahnaf Munir, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Md. Bakhtiar Hasan, Md. Taslim Reza, Md. Hasanul Kabir, "Structure-Enhanced Translation from PET to CT Modality with Paired GANs", 6th ICMVA (2023), ACM, Singapore.
- 13. Md. Hamjajul Ashmafee, Tasnim Ahmed, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Md. Bakhtiar Hasan, Mst Nura Jahan, A.B.M. Ashikur Rahman, "An Efficient Transfer Learning-based Approach for Apple Leaf Disease Classification", 3rd ECCE (2023), IEEE, Chittagong, Bangladesh.
- 14. Ahmed Nusayer Ashik, Md Saimul Haque Shanto, Rizwanul Haque Khan, Md. Hasanul Kabir, and **Sabbir Ahmed**, "Recognizing Bangladeshi Traffic Signs in the Wild", 25th ICCIT (2022), IEEE, Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh.
- 15. Minhaz Kamal, Fairuz Shaiara, Chowdhury Mohammad Abdullah, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Tasnim Ahmed, and Md. Hasanul Kabir, "Huruf: An Application for Arabic Handwritten Character Recognition Using Deep Learning", 25th ICCIT (2022), IEEE, Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh.
- 16. Akib Mohammed Khan, Alif Ashrafee, Reeshoon Sayera, Shahriar Ivan, and **Sabbir Ahmed**, "Rethinking Cooking State Recognition with Vision Transformers", 25th ICCIT (2022), IEEE, Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh.
- 17. Refaat Mohammad Alamgir, Ali Abir Shuvro, Mueeze Al Mushabbir, Mohammed Ashfaq Raiyan, Nusrat Jahan Rani, Md Rahman, Md Kabir, and **Sabbir Ahmed**, "Performance Analysis of YOLO-based Architectures for Vehicle Detection from Traffic Images in Bangladesh", 25th ICCIT (2022), IEEE, Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh.
- 18. Md. Samin Morshed, **Sabbir Ahmed**, Tasnim Ahmed, Muhammad Usama Islam, and A. B. M. Rahman, "Fruit quality assessment with densely connected convolutional neural network", 12th ICECE (2022), IEEE, Dhaka, Bangladesh,
- 19. Arowa Yasmeen, Fariha Ishrat Rahman, **Sabbir Ahmed**, and Md Hasanul Kabir, "CSVC-Net: Code-switched voice command classification using deep CNN-LSTM network", 10th ICIEV (2021), IEEE, Kitakyushu, Japan.
- 20. Ayesha Khatun, Mohammad Sajid Shahriar, Md Hasibul Hasan, Krishna Das, **Sabbir Ahmed**, and Md Sakibul Islam, "A systematic review on the chronological development of Bangla sign language recognition systems", 10th ICIEV (2021), IEEE, Kitakyushu, Japan.

Ongoing Research Projects

· Leaf Disease Detection with Limited Data

Exploring different Deep Learning techniques to achieve high performance with limited amount of data.

· Pest Detection from images taken in the wild

Investigating the use of Deep learning techniques to effectively detect and segment pests from real-life images.

Bangledeshi Traffic Sign Detection Benchmark

Curating a dataset containing traffic sign images representing real-life challenges from road of Bangladesh.

Training and Workshop

• Day long workshop on Outcome Based Education (OBE)

2021

Location: Gazipur, Bangladesh

Content: Detailed introduction of the terminologies regarding OBE to apply in course curriculum

Software Quality Assurance for Web Development

2018

Islamic University of Technology

Location: Gazipur, Bangladesh

Content: Quality assurance and cyber security

Workshop: Project management and software testing tools

Other Experiences

Reviewer

Journal: IEEE Access (6), Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence- Elsevier (1), Connection Science - Taylor & Francis (1)

Conference: ICIEV- IEEE (3)

Advisor

2018 - Present

IUT Programming Community (IUTPC), IUT Computer Society (IUTCS)

Regional Mentor

2021 - 2022

Smart Agro-Technology Innovation Youth Network (SAIYN), Bangladesh Agricultural University (BAU)

Honors and Awards

2021
2018
2016
2016
2015
2014
2012

Extra-Curricular Activities

• Vice President, IUT Computer Society (IUTCS)

2016 - 2017

• Organizer, 9th National ICT Fest, IUT

2017

Links

- ORCiD: orcid.org/my-orcid?orcid=0000-0001-5928-4886
- LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/sabbirahmediut

References

• Dr. Md. Hasanul Kabir

Professor
Department of Computer Science and Engineering
Islamic University of Technology
Email: hasanul@iut-dhaka.edu

• Dr. Abu Raihan Mostafa Kamal

Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Islamic University of Technology *Email:* raihan.kamal@iut-dhaka.edu